<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true copie of an edict, made by the king of Spaine, concerning the new Christians dwelling in Portugall, and of their departure out of his saide realmes &amp; dominions, freely without molestation, or losse of their goodes, and also of free libertie to them graunted, for their returne againe into his realmes and dominions: whensoever they shall thinke good. Translated out of the Portugall language, into English. 1602</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1602. English</title>
            <author>Spain. Sovereign (1598-1621 : Philip III)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09864</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20128</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101931</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837734</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837734</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2074</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09864)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2074)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1033:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true copie of an edict, made by the king of Spaine, concerning the new Christians dwelling in Portugall, and of their departure out of his saide realmes &amp; dominions, freely without molestation, or losse of their goodes, and also of free libertie to them graunted, for their returne againe into his realmes and dominions: whensoever they shall thinke good. Translated out of the Portugall language, into English. 1602</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1602. English</title>
                  <author>Spain. Sovereign (1598-1621 : Philip III)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. B[lower] for Thomas Pauier,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1602]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Portugese original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  Spain --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Portugal --  History --  Spanish dynasty, 1580-1640.</term>
               <term>Portugal --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2074:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2074:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> True Copie of an Edict, made by the King of Spaine, concerning the new Chriſtians Dwelling in Portugall, and of their departure out of his ſaide Realmes &amp; Dominions, freely without moleſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or loſſe of their goodes, and alſo of free libertie to them graunted, for their returne againe into his Realmes and Dominions: whenſoever they ſhall thinke good.</p>
            <p>(⸫)</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the Portugall lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, into Engliſh. 1602.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> At LONDON, Printed by R. B. for Thomas Pauier.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="edict">
            <pb facs="tcp:2074:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2074:2"/>
            <head>A True Copie of the King of Spaines late Edict, touching the Chriſtians &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Orde <hi>PHILLIP,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>by the grace of God, I giue to vnderſtand vnto all thoſe to whom this my Letter, or Edict ſhall come, to be ſéene or read, that <hi>George Rochiges Soles,</hi> and <hi>Rodrigo Dandrades,</hi> Atturneys, or Solicitors, of théeſe new Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, which are dwelling or inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting within any of my Realmes, Lordeſhips and Dominions, did earneſtly Requeſt of me, that I ſhould graunt them ſo much fauour, as to Chardge and Commaunde that al ſuch Lawes, Statutes, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, which were eſtabliſhed and made by the King my Lorde and Father, which is in Glory, and by other Lordes and Kinges his predeceſſors, touching the new Chriſtians inhabiting and dwelling within the Realme of Portugall, might be quite revoked and made fruſtrate: by which ſaid Lawes, Statutes and Ordinances, the ſaide perſons were prohibited and forbidden that they ſhoulde not departe out of the ſaide Realmes, Dominions and Lordeſhips, without expreſſe Leaue and Licence: and for to ſell their goodes and Landes: whereupon the ſaid Atturneyes or Solicitors for theſe new Chriſtians haue as aforeſaide moſt erneſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2074:3"/>and deſired, that from that time forwardes it might be lawfull to and for any of the ſaide new Chriſtians, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part and go their wayes fréely out of the ſaide Kingdomes Dominions and Lordeſhips, and alſo for to returne backe againe at all times whenſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe them, with their families and goodes, without any offence vnto any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: and not to be bounde at any time hereafter, to aſke or demaunde any Leaue or Licenſe at all, and likewiſe that I ſhoulde giue them frée leaue and licenſe to ſell their goodes and Landes at all times when they ſhall thinke méete and convenient for their owne benefit and good. And that from hencefoorth, nor at any time hereafter, there ſhall be any Lawes, Statutes, or Ordinances whatſoeuer, made or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned in contradiction of this Edict. And that it woulde pleaſe vs of our gratious fauour and goodnes, to pardon all thoſe perſons whatſoeuer, which haue heeretofore at any time or times, departed out of any of our Kingdomes, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions and Lordſhips, and haue ſolde and put away their goodes and Lands contrary to the ſaid former Lawes, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and Ordinances, and alſo that wée ſhoulde Chardge and Commaunde that all ſuch pretentions, accuſations, or moleſtation of them, or any of them, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this time forwarde ſhall ceaſe. And forasmuch as they do partly knowe the great want which my Treaſury doth ſuſtaine, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing of my goodes, and by reaſon of the loyall loue and good will which they beare vnto me, as my true and loyall Subiects: they haue beſtowed vpon me <hi>17050.</hi> duccats towardes the Coſt and chardges thereof. And that as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this Decrée, there might an Edict be made, which may remaine in force, and be eſtabliſhed for a Law, with a Contract irrevocable, and to that intent and purpoſe, that I ſhoulde graunt them their requeſt and petition aforeſaid, they aledged before me, certaine Reaſons and Cauſes to moue me to do the ſame: The which I commaunded to be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2074:3"/>ſéene &amp; pervſed, and alſo throughly examined by my lawes and Satutes, before the Lordes of my Royall Councell, and by other wiſe, diſcréet, and wiſe perſonages, throughly and well to examine the ſaide caſe, and to cauſe good proofes to be made thereof, and of ſuch Informations as are néede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and requiſite. Whereupon, now it doth appeare by thoſe Lawes and accuſations, that the ſaide new Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans haue receiued great Troubles, and ouermuch punniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And in conſideration of this heauy burthen, which they haue carried and ſuſteyned. Wée therefore finde it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conuenient and néedefull, and alſo requiſite for vs to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe them out of this bondage and thralldome, and that it were requiſite it ſhoulde be ſo done and kept for the good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerment and publique Weale of theſe my Kingdomes and Lordſhipps, and immagining that they will eſtéeme well of this my Gracious <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uour to them in this behalfe exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and alſo acknowledge them ſelues greatly beholding vnto vs, and that by reaſon of their loyall Loue and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and many other kinde of Fauours by them ſhewed and done: I do holde it for good and convenient, to Reuoke and vtterly make fruſtrat all thoſe Lawes, Statutes and Ordinances whatſoeuer, wherein it is prohibited that the ſaide new Chriſtians ſhoulde not departe out of my ſaide Realmes, Dominions and Lordeſhips, nor foorth of them, nor to ſel their goodes nor inheritances, without my ſpeciall Licenſe. And therefore I doe Commaunde and will that from hencefoorth they may depart and goe out of my ſaide Realmes with their families &amp; moueables, or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out them, &amp; that they may returne backe againe at all times, without any moleſting or apprehending of them, and that none ſhal accuſe them for departing out of my ſaide Realmes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out leaue or licenſe: And that likewiſe they may ſell their ſaid goodes at all times whenſoeuer they ſhall thinke conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, fréely without aſking any leaue or licenſe at all, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2074:4"/>I do further ordaine and holde it for good, that from hence forwardes, thiefe my ſaid Lawes, Statutes &amp; Ordinances, ſhall neuer be Revoked, but to ſtande and abide irreuocable for euer: inſomuch, that I thinke it neceſſarie, for diuers &amp; ſundry cauſes me thereunto mouing: as firſt, for the ſeruice of God, Secondly, for mine Eſtate and Honor, and thirdly for the great benefit and commoditie that may ariſe &amp; come, vnto my ſaide Realmes, Dominions and Lordſhips. And I do likewiſe holde it for good, and it is my will and pleſure fréely, to pardon and forgiue all thoſe which heretofore haue departed and gone away at any time, before the publication of this my Letter of Edict, out of my ſaid Realmes, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Lordſhips, and haue ſolde their ſaide goodes and inheritances without leaue or licence.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, I do ſtrictly commaund and charge, that this Edict nor any part thereof be fruſtrated, nor to procéede in any thing, directly, or indirectly, againſt the ſame, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Demaundes, Cauſes and prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cions before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, which hath bin done and executed againſt all ſuch as haue bin accuſed, and Condempned, and haue bin tryed by order of law, and paſt in iudgment, ſhall for euer hereafter, ceaſe, and not proceade any further. All which I do Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde to be performed, done and kept, by vertue of thiefe my Letters Patents by me now confirmed, Signed, and Sealed with my Royall Saale depending therevnto: The which ſhall ſtande, abide, remaine, continue and be, with all the force, effect, and Vigour of the law, and alſo that the Contractes and agréements herein mencioned and expreſſed for euer hereafter, to be irrevocable: and that all the ſame wholie, ſhal be accompliſhed, performed and kept, in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry degree, according to the true meaning &amp; Contents there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, without any Trouble, Let, Hindrance, or Imperage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof at all.</p>
            <p>And further I do deſire and intreat, all thoſe Kinges and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2074:4"/>Princes, (my Succeſſors) which hereafter ſhall ſuccéede me, for to accompliſh, maintaine and kéepe this Edict, and alſo to commaunde and cauſe the ſame to be fulfilled &amp; kept, as firmly, and in as lardge and ample manner, as by thiefe my Letters Pattents in all poynts do containe, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the whole Contents thereof. And the ſaide <hi>17050</hi> Duccats which is paide by the ſaide new Chriſtians, in that forme and manner afore mentioned in a Scedule of mine, which as concerning this Caſe, I did ſende, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded it to paſſe, and ſo to be Regiſtred.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Giuen</hi> at <hi>Madrill,</hi> 
                  <date>the Fowerth of Aprill, 1602.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anthony Fernandis d' Sorſes,</hi> did do it in the yeare of our Lorde, <hi>1601.</hi> and <hi>Anthony Aluares de Senedo,</hi> did cauſe this to be Written.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
